We don't want to buy no lino nor nothin'.
- Mr dragore, please.
- Oh, "im.
No sound, please.
After two years I find you.
I want the eternal light.
You found me too late.
It's no longer mine.
I can kill with this from
the end of the room.
No lies, please.
You cannot kill in england, mahmoud.
They... they get their murderers here,
and... hang them.
I have not come alone.
If I hang, there are others.
The eternal light goes back to the tomb
from which you stole it.
- But I tell you, I have not got it!
- Please, I am not a child.
I... I sold it.
To whom did you sell it?
To professor morlant.
That robber of the dead.
Has he sold it?
- He did not buy to sell.
- What then?
- Like you, mahmoud. He believes.
- Believes?
He believes that the eternal light...
Will open for him the gates of paradise?
Even so...
He gave the best part
of his fortune for it.
And very soon he will know whether
or not he was right.
What do you mean?
Professor morlant...
Is dying!
Then you think it will be buried with him?
I'm sure of it.
We have only got to wait...
Until he is dead.
I'm near death...
Opener of the way.
What's that?
Well, what is it?
Good evening.
I happen to be staying
in the neighbourhood...
And hearing of your master's illness,
I took the Liberty of calling.
How is he tonight?
He'll never see the morning.
He hasn't asked for anyone of my cloth?
Nor will he.
He's set in his ways...
And they're the ways of the heathen.
I know he won't see the rector...
But though I'm a comparative stranger, I
don't like to leave a man to die like that.
He'll die in his own fashion...
- As he has lived.
- Still, sometimes at the end...
Not with him.
He's stubborn and unbending.
And will be so at the throne itself.
Well, I suppose I can be of no use, then.
No manner of use.
Goodnight.
He's asking for you.
Where can I find mr broughton?
Who is it?
Come in or go out!
You'll have to go up soon, if you
want to see him again.
Curious house, this.
Curious owner.
Yes, but I suppose a great egyptologist
can't be expected to be like other people.
Well, he'll be like a great
many other people soon.
That's not a very sympathetic thing to say.
I'm not a sympathetic man.
Want a drink?
That's, uh... across the hall, isn't it?
I daresay.
Thanks.
Seventy-five thousand...
September twenty-second,
nineteen thirty-one.
Daily journal.
Nineteen...
Twenty-two.
The eternal light...
Mine at last.
- I want to see laing... laing.
- I'm here.
Is the door shut?
It is.
- No listeners?
- None.
- The curtains.
- They are drawn.
Come nearer.
This man, broughton...
Watch... broughton.
You were always suspicious.
Have you ever trusted a living soul?
Only fools.
I trust you.
Better to trust in the
spirit than in the flesh.
I put my trust...
In my own gods.
And now... when I am dead...
My funeral.
You will bury me at dusk...
In the clothes I told you.
You will place the figure of Anubis...
At the west of the inner chamber.
I will.
And on the night...
Of the full moon...
At the first hour...
I will make my offering
of the eternal light...
To Anubis...
Opener of the ways.
If I have done well in his sight...
Those fingers will
close over the Jewel...
And he will open to me
the gates of immortality.
The hand of a heathen image
will no come to life.
Ahh... the bandage, the bandage.
Look.
This... is the eternal light.
It must rest... in my hand.
A man will no find peace
who robs his heirs.
Bandage my hand.
The eternal light...
Must lie with me...
In the tomb.
You're afraid of me?
I'm afraid for you.
If this should leave me...
Then you'll have reason... to fear.
For when the full moon strikes
the door of my tomb...
I will come back.
You hear?
I will come back... to kill!
Bandage...
My hand.
Doctor! Doctor!
Doctor!
Window...
Open... oh... oh...
It's all over.
Make out a certificate. Heart failure.
What was the idea of bandaging
his hand like that?
I cannae say.
He had many a queer fancy.
I'll be round in the morning
to sign the certificate.
I'll no' be leaving my master's side
til his body is laid to rest.
Ah.
Where are you going?
To feed the lamp that is to burn inside.
- It shouldn't be allowed.
- It's all wrong.
Wait... you're leaving the key inside.
Aye... that was another
of his queer fancies.
When your master died, laing, I believe him to
have been possessed of a Jewel of great value.
Do you know anything about it?
Nothing.
I advise you to be very careful, laing.
I have a careful nature.
You may be putting yourself
perilously near dishonesty.
I've seen men nearer.
You may regret this, laing.
Davies.
I want you to stay here and watch
that man with the club foot.
I'm not a detective, mr broughton.
One more word from you, Davies,
and you're out of work.
I have reason to believe that he has
stolen a valuable piece of property.
He may make an effort to get rid of it.
Watch him... and telephone me at my
office if he leaves the house.
Very good, sir.
Harlon.
Miss Betty harlon.
52 blandford street.
Carrier!
From repson's.
Ten shillings if you'll drive me to yaxford
station, in time to catch the five o'clock train.
I'll oblige yer, guv'nor.
I was going straight back, as it was.
That's a very old carpet, mr morlant, I should
be glad if you will not kick it to pieces.
I'm sorry, but when I'm angry I do kick.
Would you like to explain that?
Yes, I intend to.
By your own statement, miss harlon and I
are the sole heirs of professor morlant.
We were informed neither of his death,
nor of his funeral.
Your uncle died and was buried in a certain
way, according to his wishes, which...
Need I go on?
Almost his last words were a
threat to return from the dead.
In my opinion, he was mad.
Well, that may be so.
But, miss harlon and I should
have been consulted.
But I understood that you and
miss harlon were not on speaking terms.
Oh, what of that? You expect quiet
at a funeral, don't you?
Yes, I also expected...
I'm very sorry but, after all, this means
a good deal to both of us.
- My uncle was worth about four thousand a year.
- Well, he isn't now.
What do you mean by that?
He spent a good deal, you know?
It may surprise you to know that some
time ago, he drew a cheque for £75,000.
What for?
I don't know.
You don't know? You were in charge of
all his affairs, and you don't know?
That is what I said.
And I advise you to look after
the tone of your voice.
I'm not at all sure I haven't much more important
things to look after than the tone of my voice.
I don't follow you.
I'm going to run down to earlsvale house
tomorrow morning.
Yes, well I... I don't
think you realise the...
Conditions that you will find there.
- No, that's why I propose to go.
- You won't like it.
You'll be most uncomfortable.
You don't advise me to go?
I think you'll be making
a very big mistake.
Then I'll go!
Oh, by the way...
Does miss harlon know anything
about this will business?
No doubt she will have received
a letter from me by now.
- Do you know miss harlon?
- No.
I propose to give myself the pleasure
of calling upon her this evening.
Hello.
Oh, it's you, Davies. Wait a minute.
I have a visitor here, but
I think he's just going.
Thank you very much.
If you're going to see miss harlon tonight,
I shall be there myself.
No doubt you will succeed in making a
painful interview intolerable.
Good afternoon.
Your manner must help your
practice a great deal.
Now, Davies...
Can you direct me to
blandford street, please?
Follow the tram lines, close on a mile
and then turn right at the church.
I'm obliged to you.
Oh, hello kaney.
Ooh!
Oohh! Oh, it's good to get out of that fog.
My dear, a most exciting
thing has happened.
Oh, don't let it happen again!
No - not that, that's a Chestnut.
It's this.
It looks like a solicitor's letter.
It's just been delivered by hand.
Ooh, dear...
What haven't we paid?
I wonder if I'm going
to get a shock or not!
Oh, kaney - that is a silly game.
After all we've said about uncle Henry...
What do you think he's done?
- Something nice at last?
- Well, he's dead.
My dear, I'm sorry.
And his solicitor wants to see me.
My dear, I'm glad.
He was awfully rich, wasn't he?
Oh! He may have left you a fortune!
- If he has, I'll buy you a private cinema.
- Oh!
I say... when did this letter come?
A few minutes ago. Why?
He asked me to telephone him,
if I could see him here at six.
You don't want to miss the chance of a
fortune, for the sake of tuppence!
- You'd better run out and do it now.
- You're right!
- Miss harlon?
- Yes.
What's the matter? What's happened?
Somebody attacked me and snatched my bag.
- Why, good lord! It's Betty harlon.
- Ralph morlant.
You would go and get yourself into
some kind of mix up.
- You would arrive when it's all over.
- Thank you.
- Well, I'm going home.
- Wait a minute.
I was on my way to see
you, strictly on business.
Well, you wouldn't be allowed in
for any other reason.
That's good.
Taxi!
Penningham garage - as quickly as possible.
Oh, so you've brought him.
Dear mr broughton, we're
delighted to see you.
No, it isn't mr broughton.
It's my cousin - Ralph morlant.
Dear mr morlant, we're
delighted to see you.
- Wrong again! We don't like him very much.
- Oh, don't we?
I didn't realise.
Well, our two families are
not on speaking terms.
Oh, dear.
As far as I can make out, it was started by
my late uncle as a Christmas joke.
Oh...!
- Won't you sit down?
- Thank you.
But now he's dead, the trouble's all over.
I'm not sure it hasn't just begun.
Where's mr broughton?
Oh, he won't come because
I didn't telephone.
I nearly got throttled instead.
- Betty!
- There was a man with a limp.
He pushed a note into my hand.
I just put it in my bag...
When somebody snatched the whole affair.
What was in it?
"There's something of value at earlsvale.”
"Others are after it..."
"So come."
And broughton was doing everything he knew
to keep me away from there.
There's a fox in the cover, somewhere!
Goodbye.
Well, why goodbye?
I'm going down there right away.
I'll let you know what happens.
You're wrong - I'll let myself know.
If you go, I go too.
You can't do that!
Alone in a house, with a man you're
not even on speaking terms with!
Oh, don't be so absurd... it's not
as if I even liked him.
If another woman was going, perhaps.
I suppose that means you want to come too?
Well, obviously - it's my duty.
And suppose I object?
I'm not so broke I can't hire a car.
Oh, all right - you win. But
for goodness' sake, hurry!
Girls - you must get in this as
best you can. There you are.
You first.
No, you - hurry up.
- Ooh, this is an unspeakable car!
- There's no room for my legs!
All right, all right!
It looks as if I'll have to walk.
You might do worse... there's a grand moon.
It's full.
I'll see if there's a name on this gate.
No, there's nothing to
show this is the place.
But there aren't any other
places, and I'm frozen.
Well, it's no use going to the wrong place.
Wait a minute, here's someone on a bike.
Hi there, cocky - wait a minute.
Oh, hello.
Oh, I'm awfully sorry - I didn't see
you were a parson.
Oh, that's all right.
- Any trouble?
- Oh, no - no.
We just want to get to earlsvale house.
Well, this is it.
As a matter of fact I'm
calling there myself.
- Did you know my uncle, professor morlant?
- Oh, slightly.
Perhaps I ought to introduce myself.
My name's hartley, Nigel hartley.
- I'm down at raveley. The... the vicar's ill.
- How do you do?
I'm Ralph morlant.
This is miss harlon.
We're the heirs of...
- Couldn't we have the rest of the introduction indoors?
- Yes, yes - of course. You must be cold.
- It's straight down this drive. You go along - I'll follow.
- All right.
Here we are.
Car'll be all right here.
I'll show you the way.
What a horrible house!
I wish I was back home in bed.
I can hear someone coming.
Ah!
Well, don't stand about. Come inside.
We'll go into the library.
I may be old-fashioned, but I feel awkward
when I'm not introduced to people.
I'm sorry, I forgot you didn't know
your clients by sight.
This is miss harlon.
How do you do?
I was expecting a telephone
message from you.
Oh, I was on my way to call you up...
When the most extraordinary
thing happened.
And this is miss kaney.
How do you do?
You're a surprise, broughton.
I have a great deal of business to
clear up down here.
This house has needed a woman
for about twenty-five years.
Eugh! Now I've blinded myself.
You haven't wasted much time in getting
here, mr morlant.
No! Just a little too much perhaps?
Whatever do you mean?
Really! You're the rudest man alive.
Oh, pretty pussy!
How horrible! It's stuffed.
I daresay you know your own business best.
But why you should want
to bring a parson...?
- A pure accident. We met at the gates.
- So, naturally, you brought him in.
Broughton, I can stand a
certain amount - but no more.
Ah, come, come. Don't let's
make a battle of it.
- You stay here in the car.
- No!
I shall be among the trees... watching.
You may say I have no right to
express this opinion...
But to my mind it's a scandalous
and disgraceful burial...
Which may have disastrous consequences.
It'd be very disastrous if he came
back, wouldn't it?
I quite see mr hartley's point.
- Yes, you make friends quickly, don't you?
- And enemies quicker.
Need we have these childish squabbles?
We all know that dead men don't come back.
Oh! I wish I was back home in bed!
Hadn't somebody better answer that?
Certainly.
- It's your house.
- Very well.
I'm sorry to disturb you.
But I was an intimate friend
of professor morlant.
Well, you'd better come in.
- We seem to be giving a party.
- Oh!
Well, thank you.
My name is aga Ben dragore.
An Egyptian?
An arab!
I don't remember having heard your name.
I did not flatter myself that you would.
But I knew professor
morlant, some years ago.
In Egypt.
I heard of his death.
And of his burial, in my own faith.
And I hoped, as I am leaving
england tomorrow...
That I might be allowed
to visit his tomb.
I must protest against
anything of the sort.
Why shouldn't the poor man look
at his friend's tomb?
I don't mind him going.
I can't believe that you'd willingly
encourage paganism.
The Egyptians were not pagans, sir.
As no doubt you know miss... er...?
Kaney.
I think you're all being
very unkind to mr dragore.
I don't think you people realise quite
how far morlant's queer ideas took him.
He even believed that after his death...
At a certain hour...
The image of Anubis would come
to life in his tomb...
And receive his soul.
It's horrible!
Well, I can't see that it matters.
After all, if that sort of mumbo-jumbo
gave him any comfort I...
It matters a great deal.
If my suggestion is likely to
hurt anyone's feelings...
Please forget it.
Oh, I think that's very
sweet of you, mr dragore.
Oh, your sympathy is more than charming.
Well? What about a cup of coffee
after your cold drive?
I daresay we should find
some in the kitchen.
May I offer my services, as pantry man?
Quite sweet of you.
Come, mr dragore.
For sheer speed! She'll not let him
out of her sight now.
Perhaps that's just as well.
Come along, Betty. How about
making a fire in the library?
Yes.
I'm sorry there should be this
sort of atmosphere.
After all, we're only ships
that pass in the night.
Hmm.
Do you want a drink, or will you pass now?
Oh, well, thank you very much.
There you are.
Well, if you build it that way there
won't be any draught.
Oh? It'll be the only place in this house
where there isn't one then.
Oh, don't you think you carry those
snappy retorts a trifle too far?
And since we've met, I can't remember
you saying a kind word to anyone.
Perhaps you're right.
I'm sorry.
Six cups.
That's just...
Just four too many - eh?
Tell me about Egypt.
Have you ever seen a sheikh?
I am one!
Oh, thank you.
Then how should I address you?
Oh, I'm cutting sandwiches for a sheikh!
I don't feel quite well.
Oh, don't be alarmed.
We're not quite as
uncivilised as people think.
- Oh, don't say that!
- Hmm?
Do you ride a white stallion?
- Sometimes.
- Oh!
Down the path of the moon.
The noble animal, plunging and
frothing at the nostrils...
Til it founders at your
feet, faithful unto death.
Well, not very often.
You see, it's rather too expensive.
Oh, I know it's not your fault...
We were taught to
hate one another, but...
Good lord, you don't think I
hate you, do you?
Well, I can't somehow feel I'm
your dearest friend.
You never did have a great deal
of sense, did you?
Oh, that's nice.
Ralph?
I've a woman's intuition that you and
I are up against things.
Yes, I'm pretty sure we are.
Well, then... let's cut the quarrelling.
Shoulder to shoulder, eh? All right.
Partners.
- Partners.
- Ha!
Well, what a wonderful night.
It's a full moon.
Scared of a dead man in his tomb?
Shame on yourself.
Are you a child that your knee should
rattle at the talk of a madman?
Look your enemy in the face.
It's the fear of the big door has got you.
And will hold you fast
'til you stare it down.
Do dead men walk?
I'm no' thinking a dead man will
cross my path tonight.
Arrrgh!
Urrgh!
Oh! I was dreaming.
Now I will show you...
How we make coffee in the desert...
Underneath the stars.
You don't make it yourself, do you?
No, of course not.
A circassian slave - lovely as sin -
cooks it for us, kneeling.
- And if it is not to our liking...
- I know!
She's stripped to the waist...
And lashed for miles across the Sahara.
Where she is finally eaten - by locusts.
And rightly.
Now, take this canister and
do exactly as I tell you.
Oh!
And if I fail?
The Yorkshire moors are just behind us.
Now.
Six spoonfuls.
One!
Two!
Three!
Four!
Five!
Get off you!
Take your arms away from...
What's the matter with you?
Are you mad, eh?
What was the matter with him?
- Was it drink?
- No!
Terror!
- Stark terror!
- Oooh!
Then I've caught it!
You stay here.
I'll look after him.
If you must look after somebody,
why look further?
Eh?
Come on, then.
Ralph!
That limp. I'd swear to it anywhere.
That's the man!
- Look here, did you give a note to this young lady?
- Gather up your things and get out of here!
The master... I've seen him!!!
Who screamed?
I did!
That's the last time I'll ever try to make
coffee in a strange house.
- That man with the limp - who was he?
- Laing.
Your uncle's servant.
Well, he seemed mad to me.
Yes.
And probably dangerous.
You others had better go into the library.
I'll have a word with him.
Yes, come along.
Mr broughton understands the man.
It would do no harm to warn
my man to stand by.
Your man?
- Is he a sheikh, too?
- No, no - he's a chauffeur.
He's outside now, with my car.
You're not leaving us, are you?
My dear lady.
Not a very courageous
person, our foreign friend.
You think he's run away?!
Absurd!
I'd like to see you riding your bicycle...
With a circassian slave, lovely
as sin, across the handlebars!
- What on earth are you talking about?
- Now listen, good people.
"Good people?”
Don't you think perhaps we are allowing
this thing to get on our nerves?
Don't you think perhaps if we took
a grip on our self-control...
Now listen, good parson.
This is our show, and our nerves are
probably just as good as the next man's.
So keep that sort of talk for your pulpit.
Ralph!
Oh, well, of course, I've no wish
to interfere where I'm not wanted.
Then don't. This is not a Sunday school.
After that, I think I can say "good night".
As you please.
Well, I'm sorry I was offensive.
Good night.
Oh, well, the tongue is an
unruly member - is it not?
- Yes.
- Yes...
I was tempted.
I was tempted, but I did not fall.
I did not fall.
The thing's safe.
I swear it.
When you told me you'd come
back from the grave...
How could I believe you?
I never knew such things could be.
No!
Oh...! Arrgh!
I have no' got it. I have no' got it!
The girl - she has it!
I swear it!
Oh! Oh!
What on earth's the matter with you?
You look as if you've seen a ghost.
I have!
I saw morlant...
As plainly as I see you.
I'm going to mix meself a drink.
Betty? Just a minute.
Well?
I've an idea they're trying to scare us
out of this house.
Now, there's no use blinding
ourselves to the facts.
There must be something
pretty big at stake.
Something that depends
on getting rid of us?
That's how it looks to me.
Well, what are we going to do?
Who's there?
- Betty, I'm going down to that tomb to find out whether...
- But...
It's the only way we've got of finding
out what's going on around here.
Well, I don't want to be left here
alone. Can I come too?
There's nothing wrong with your nerve.
Come on.
I'll put on a pullover
and some thicker shoes.
All right.
- Is this yours?
- Yes.
I'll keep an eye on broughton.
Well, I'd think you've every chance of seeing
things if you lower scotch at that pace.
Oh!
Oh...!
Mr dragore! Mr dragore! Mr dragore!
Mr dragore!! I
oh! There you are!
Oh, mr dragore!
I'll come up to you!
Wait. I'll come down.
What do you want?
- There was somebody in the library!
- Who?
I don't know.
The door... it shut!
- It shut! I...
- Don't scream.
Oh! That's what I need.
The command in your wonderful voice.
Come with me!
I think you've gone far enough
with your insinuations.
Yes, and I may go a great deal farther.
What is it? What's the matter?
I've seen him.
Now perhaps you'll believe what I told you?
Get me a glass of water quickly, will you?
Thanks. I wasn't hurt - only frightened.
Broughton - see if you can find
miss kaney, will you?
It's wonderful to be with
a man who isn't afraid.
I am afraid.
You, who've ridden
bare-backed over the desert?
If you don't stop chattering, I'm afraid
I shall have a knife in my back.
But when I'm with you I have to talk.
It comes, like poetry.
Are you prepared to obey me?
In anything.
Then... close your eyes.
And don't speak for ten seconds.
We all panic sometimes.
- I felt his hands on me.
- That's why I know it was no ghost.
It was no ghost.
Look at the clock.
It's nearing the hour.
I know where you'll find him now.
He's gone back to the tomb.
To his heathen gods.
Then you and I will follow him there.
Wait a minute.
- What's his doctor's telephone number?
- Yaxford 72.
Look!
The door's open and there's a light.
I'll go no nearer.
I can see a shadow moving.
I'll go no nearer!
Well then, go back.
What about it, Betty?
Do we go on?
Yes, of course.
Thought you'd say that.
Oh...!
No...
Aieeeel!!
Look!
Hartley!
So, you're not a parson.
Just a dirty crook!
You'd better get out of my way.
Your hand, eh?
So, that's how it was done.
- I wouldn't come any nearer.
- I don't have to!
Look!
If you please!
Thank you. Come on now.
Go!
- Come on, it's too late. Are you badly hurt?
- No, no - it's nothing.
Come and sit down.
Where's the key?
He threw it away.
When I phoned the doctor I told
him to bring the police.
They ought to find us somehow.
Why, even if they do come, how can
they break down that door?
They'll find a way.
I'll make a bandage.
The doctor in charge didn't
understand the case.
- I'm afraid of catalepsy.
- Meaning?
Morlant was buried alive.
Oh, mr dragore!
What were those shots?
- Out of my way.
- Where are the others?
Leave me alone!
Ooh! Oh! Oooh!
I rather thought you might
be leaving in a hurry...
With something in your pocket
that doesn't belong to you.
Hand it over.
You win!
That woman!
There she is!
Come now.
Oh, you put down that gun, you fool!
I tell you, she's got it
come on, man.
Stop!
Now, miss kaney - if you please.
I don't think so.
You fool.
If either of you two horrible men...
So much as move...
In it goes.
But you don't know the value of that Jewel.
I don't care for the value. It'll go!
And if you shoot...
I'lll go with it.
I mean it.
Down thirty feet.
And about sixty feet of water, and,
and... and then, Australia.
Well, I can't see to tie this.
That light seems much lower.
Hartley! Quick, come on - get up.
Get him out of here.
Right.
- The door! The door!
- It's shut!
The flames - they mustn't reach the door!
It's no good. You can't breathe in there.
The cartridge.
It's here. If only...
If only...
I've had enough of this, miss kaney.
Supposing I'm ready to
shoot, and take the risk?
You'd be taking a bigger
risk than you think.
I'll take that gun, thank you.
- Now look here!
- That'll do.
Now, what's the trouble?
This.
They're after it.
All of them.
It belongs...
I'll carry her to the house.
Get back!
Get to that corner!